Guide to the Ku Klux Klan Collection, 1916-1987 and undated RL.10138
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ku Klux Klan collection
1916-1987 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ku Klux Klan (1915- )
RL.10138
5 Linear Feet
Twentieth-century secret fraternal group held to confine its membership to American-born white Protestant Christians. Collection includes a broad range of Ku Klux Klan pamphlets, flyers, and other ephemera regarding Klan membership, Anglo-American values, protests against African Americans, Communists, or non-Protestant people, and promotional Klan events. Early material highlights activities of the Women of the Klan in Pennsylvania during the 1920s, including their charity work and fundraising for the Klan Haven, an orphanage. This material also includes large panoramic photographs of 1920s Klan reunions. Later materials from the 1960s are largely from the Southeast and mid-Atlantic States, and include literature, flyers, and handouts on Klan history, segregation, school integration, Communism, Catholicism, and Judaism.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
[Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Ku Klux Klan Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library beginning in the 1960s. It has been acquired through gifts and purchases by the library.
Historical Note
The Ku Klux Klan is a federally classified hate group first established following the Civil War. It advocates a white supremacist, pro-nationalist, anti-immigration America, and historically has used terrorist and intimidation tactics. The first Klan largely died out in the 1870s. The group revived in the 1920s as nativist and anti-Communist, while the third Klan re-emerged following World War II to oppose the Civil Rights movement.
Collection Overview
Collection includes printed materials, apologetics, membership solicitations, circulars, brochures, pamphlets, broadsides, periodicals, cards, ephemera, and realia. Items were produced and distributed by various chapters of the Ku Klux Klan, dispersed throughout the United States, but largely originating in the Southeast and Mid-Atlantic region. The KKK Collection also includes several panoramic photographs, assorted issues of Klan and other hate-group serial titles, and audio materials.
Materials have been acquired from a variety of sources and over several decades. Most of the collection has been arranged according to the geographic origin of the materials. Different branches and factions of the Klan are represented, including the United Klans of America, Women of the Ku Klux Klan, the Invisible Empire of the KKK, the Mississippi Green Knights, and the Mississippi White Knights.
Notable items include: a petition for the incorporation of a Klan chapter in Fulton Co., Georgia, in 1916; panoramic photographs and a wallet with Klan membership cards from Charles D. Johnson, a Florida Klansman in the 1930s; 1920s order forms for Klan robes, fiery crosses, and other Klan administrative materials from the Women of the Klan; pamphlets, circulars, and other literature opposing the Civil Rights movement, desegregation, and school integration, collected in Alabama, Mississippi, and Louisiana in the 1960s; and recruitment flyers for rallies in Maryland, Ohio, and Pennsylvania during the 1980s.
Other items were first distributed during a talk by C. P. Ellis to freshmen students at a Duke University dormitory in 1969. Items include a 45-rpm sound disc with the songs "Flight NAACP 105" and "High ride"; a flyer regarding protests against the playing of the song "Dixie" at student events; a membership form for the North Carolina chapter; and printed items, including God is the Author of Segregation (1967) and issues of The Fiery Cross.
Sound recordings; Apologetics -- History -- 20th century; Racism -- United States; Racism -- United States -- Periodicals; Audiovisual materials; United States -- Race relations; Tupelo (Miss.) -- History; McComb (Miss.) -- History; Fulton County (Ga.) -- History; Propaganda, Anti-communist; Antisemitism; White supremacy movements -- United States; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- Florida; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- Georgia; George Washington Flowers Collection of Southern Americana; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- Alabama; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- Mississippi; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- New Jersey; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- History; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- Maryland; Dudley, Frank, 1892-1956; Ellis, C. P.; Comer, Robbie Gill; Dahmer, Vernon Ferdinand, 1908-1966; Turnley, Martha; Swift, Wesley A.; Women of the Ku Klux Klan -- Pennsylvania; Venable, James; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ); Penn, Lemuel; Lentz, Albert P.; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- Ohio; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- North Carolina; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- Periodicals; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- Pennsylvania
- Ku Klux Klan Materials
  Scope and Contents
  General Klan materials dating from the 1910s through the 1980s. Items have been sorted geographically by origin. Contents include Klan recruitment posters and flyers, literature about the Klan and its activities, clippings, correspondence, and general hate speech from Klan chapters and leaders.
  - Alabama Klan (general), 1926 - 1931 (Box 1)
    - Blank form tracking Klan affiliations for electoral candidates in Alabama, 1926 (Box 1)
    - Mass mailings sent to C.E. Headley, Exalted Cyclops, 1925-1927 (Box 1)
      Generic correspondence collected by Headley from the Realm of Alabama. Includes subscription notices from the Kourier Magazine; Klan parade plans; financial missives; Klonverse agenda; Invisible Empire Pass Kode; and other topics.
    - "The Obligation of American Citizens to Free Public Schools" pamphlet, undated (Box 1)
    - Ku Klux Klan Annual Celebration Flyer, Birmingham, 1931 Nov. 12 (Box 1)
    - Robert E. Lee Klan recruitment letter, 1930 May 3 (Box 1)
    - Meeting minutes, Jefferson County, 1926 Nov. 10 (Box 1)
  - Alabama Headquarters of the United Klans of America, 1965-1980 (Box 1)
    - Mass mailings from the United Klans central office, 1980s (Box 1)
    - Promotional/recruitment literature, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
      Includes "What Will You Tell Your Children?," "Savagery in the Raw," arrest statistics, "Know the United Nations," Klan principles, "What You Should Know about the Rigging of Voting Machines," "Klankraft to the American Boy,"etc.
  - Florida Klan, undated (Box 1)
    - Recruitment flyers, undated (Box 1)
      Titles: "Racial Differences," "Stand Up For Your Rights! Join the Ku Klux Klan," and "Join! the Ku Klux Klan"
    - Charles D. Johnson's wallet, Miami, Florida, approximately 1936 (Box 1)
      Johnson's complete wallet, including a membership card ("passport") to the Invisible Empire of the KKK. Also includes membership cards for the American Legion, the National Motorists' Association, and United Klans of Florida, as well as automobile insurance cards.
    - Photocopy of Charlie David Johnson and Margaret Ruth Sehl marriage certificate, 12 March 1976 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Georgia Klan, 1916-1927 (Box 1)
    - Blank membership/minutes form, Atlanta, 1920s (Box 1)
    - Articles of Incorporation for the Ku Klux Klan of Fulton County, 1916 (Box 1)
    - Blank application for Klan membership, undated (Box 1)
    - Klan ID Card, Macon, Dixie Klan no. 33 (Box 1)
  - Indiana Klan, undated (Box 1)
    - Flyers and programs for events, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Recruitment materials, 1950s-1960s and undated (Box 1)
      Anti-integration, anti-miscegenation, anti-United Nations, and anti-communism literature. "I am Liberty," "A Klansman's Prayer,", "Their Peace Symbol--'The Broken Cross,'" "The Pros and Cons of the United Klans of America," "What Will You Tell Your Children," "Don't Be Half a Man, Join the Klan."
    - Whitewater Klan no. 60 letterhead, reinstatement form (Box 1)
    - "White Youth Fight Back" pamphlet, undated (Box 1)
    - "The Seven Symbols of the Klan" pamphlet, 1966 (Box 1)
    - "Council of Foreign Relations, the secret enemy" pamphlet, undated (Box 1)
    - "It's Time to Save Our Schools" pamphlet, 1960s (Box 1)
    - "Know the UN" pamphlet, undated (Box 1)
    - "Abraham Lincoln Speaks" and "Forthy Reasons for Segregation!" pamphlet, undated (Box 1)
    - "Brainwashed" by George A. McNeely pamphlet, undated (Box 1)
    - "The Truth Behind the Peace Symbol" pamphlet, undated (Box 1)
    - "Freedom of Choice the Law of the Land" pamphlet, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "The True Story of the Ku Klux Klan" pamphlet, undated (Box 1)
    - "The White Reply to the Black Manifesto", 1969 (Box 1)
    - "The Fiery Cross Bulletin: An introduction to the United Klans of America, Inc." pamphlet, undated (Box 1)
    - Promotional cards containing hate speech, undated (Box 1)
  - Ku Klux Klan (general) (Box 1)
    - Oaths of Allegiance (Box 1)
    - Cartoon drawing of Klansman (photocopy), 1920s (Box 1)
    - The Houghton Line issue on the KKK, 1923 (Box 1)
    - Poem about the Klan: Just Ask Ringold, 1923 (Box 1)
    - Klan membership acceptance letter, Form 41 (blank) (Box 1)
    - "Have You Fired Your Niggers?" propaganda card (Box 1)
    - Fiery Summons to a Klan meeting (blank) (Box 1)
    - "The Whole Truth About the Knights of the Ku Klux Klan" pamphlet, undated (Box 1)
    - "Principles and Purposes of the Knights of the Ku Klux Klan" pamphlet (Box 1)
    - Klan Robe order form, Heritage Garment Works, Columbia, S.C. (Box 1)
    - Klan recruitment postcard and poem, undated (Box 1)
  - Louisiana Klan, undated (Box 1)
    - Klan cards, undated (Box 1)
  - Maryland Klan, 1973-1987 and undated (Box 1)
    - Proclamations from Grand Dragon, 1983-1985 and undated (Box 1)
      Newsletters and printed materials from the Baltimore Klan. Includes notices about "nigger culture," "Hunting Season" flyers; "nigger employment applications"; Klan recruitment posters; and posters reading "Ground Wanted" for Klan rallies.
    - Klan rally flyers, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
      Flyers promoting rallies in Braddock Heights and Gamber, Maryland
  - Mississippi Klan (general), 1960s (Box 1)
    - Recruitment literature (Box 1)
      Patronage cards, reasons to join the Klan, and printed materials about the Klan's history.
    - "Klan Ledger" newsletter, Greenville-Anguilla, Mississippi, undated (Box 1)
    - "The Christian Conservative Communique," vol. 2, no. 5, 1966 (Box 1)
      Issue addressing "The Negro Question"
    - "A Delta Discussion" newsletter, Issues 1-4, undated (Box 1)
      Targeting citizens of Greenwood, Mississippi
    - Mississippi Parents for Segregation, 1960s (Box 1)
      Mass mailing encouraging white teachers in integrated schools to resign.
  - Mississippi Knights of the Green Forest (Tupelo, Miss.), 1967; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Sticker with Knights logo, undated (Box 1)
    - Photographs of Klan Headquarters, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Promotional and recruitment literature, 1967 and undated (Box 1)
    - Dale Walton campaign materials, 1967 (Box 1)
      Includes flyers, matchbook, nail file, and clippings about Dale Walton's campaign for sheriff
    - Application for membership, undated (Box 1)
  - Mississippi Realm of United Klans of America, 1960s (Box 1)
    - Promotional literature, 1967 (Box 1)
      "What can I do to promote Americanism?", "Some Questions that need Straight Answers," other promotional titles
    - Bumper sticker: "Unite Together White Man Register to Vote Now!", 1967 (Box 1)
    - Rally flyer for Union, Mississippi, 1966
    - Clippings about Klan activities, 1960s (Box 1)
  - Mississippi White Knights, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
    - Notice denouncing Patrick Pennington, and accompanying newspaper clipping, 1967 (Box 1)
      Klan notice denouncing Pennington for selling his house to an African American family, and an accompanying newspaper clipping from The Northside Reporter (Jackson, Miss.) defending Pennington from the slander.
    - Bulletin threatening Bill Waller campaign, and accompanying clipping, 1967 (Box 1)
      Bulletin from Local Concerned Citizens threatening to disrupt a campaign dinner for Bill Waller, and an accompanying clipping describing the explosion threats received during the dinner.
    - "The White Sentinel of Mississippi", 1966 (Box 1)
      Bulletin encouraging white citizens to vote for George Wallace, concluding: "White Supremacy is the Answer to Black Power."
    - KKK Leaflet for "People of Panola County", 1966 (Box 1)
    - KKK leaflets centering on Raleigh, Mississippi, 1965 (Box 1)
      Leaflets distributed by the Klan around Raleigh, Mississippi, denouncing Raleigh Corporation workplace practices; promoting Back to Africa programs; and opposing integration.
    - KKK leaflet for "good people of Aberdeen," Mississippi, 1967 (Box 1)
      Includes list of white citizens "consorting" with African Americans, along with details of their interactions.
    - KKK leaflet for "negroes of Chicaksaw and Calhoun Counties", undated (Box 1)
      Protesting and threatening school integration.
    - Miscellaneous Klan leaflets, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
      Include recruitment flyers, threatening bulletins, and various printed materials promoting the Klan and its activities.
    - "The Klan Ledger" newsletter, miscellaneous issues, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - "I Want You" Uncle Sam KKK recruitment poster (Box 1)
    - "Sharkey County News" newsletter, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Webster County Klan newsletter, 1966 (Box 1)
    - "Affidavit" of Deavours Nix, describing an encounter with the FBI in Laurel, Mississippi, 1966 (Box 1)
    - News clippings about the murder of Vernon Dahmer, 1967 (Box 1)
      Includes articles about FBI probe and suspect Deavours Nix.
    - "The Citizen-Patriot" leaflets, Laurel, Mississippi, 1967 (Box 1)
      Flyers/leaflets denouncing J.W. West, editor of the Laurel Leader-Call newspaper.
    - "Rebel Press" broadside, 1967 (Box 1)
      Photocopy of handwritten poster naming people and businesses sympathetic to school integration, encouraging the public to boycott those businesses.
    - Klan patronage card, undated (Box 1)
  - New Jersey Klan, undated (Box 3)
    - Recruitment posters for Klan based in Vineland, New Jersey, undated (Box 1)
  - North Carolina Klan, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    Materials distributed by C.P. Ellis at Duke University freshman dorms, 1969.
    - "God is the Author of Segregation" pamphlets (2 copies), 1967 (Box 1)
    - Flyer "Attention Students," from the Durham chapter of the United Klans of America, undated (Box 1)
    - The Fiery Cross, Vol 2, 12th edition, undated (Box 1)
  - North Carolina Klan, 1986-1990 and undated (Box 1)
    - Mass mailings to Klan members, 1986 (Box 1)
      Promoting a Raleigh Klan march and including a defense of Glenn Miller.
    - Klan essays (photocopied), undated (Box 1)
      "The Tragedy of Truth" and "The Yellow Rose of Texas"
    - Recruitment flyer for the NC Klan, Henderson, North Carolina, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Ohio Klan, 1969, 1981, and undated (Box 1)
    - "Symbols of the Klan" literature, undated (Box 1)
    - White Knights newsletters, Miamisburg, Ohio, undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence from Grand Dragon Blaine Qualls, undated (Box 1)
      Includes photocopied insert about Martin Luther King Jr.
    - Photocopied clipping about Ohio Klan from The Christian Science Monitor, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Oregon Klan, 1950s (Box 1)
    - Kentucky Klick membership application for Portland Oregon chapter, 1950s (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Klan, 1981-1987 (Box 1)
    - "The Truth" newsletter, York, Pennsylvania, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
    - Rally flyers, 1981-1987 (Box 1)
      Promoting Klan rallies in Cly, Windham Center, and Shrewsbury, Pennsylvania.
    - Wanted poster for William Alston, "escaped cop killer", undated (Box 1)
    - Recruitment posters, undated (Box 1)
  - Tennessee Realm of United Klans of America, 1960s (Box 1)
    - Mass mailing solicitations for funds from C.C. Cozart, Donating Chairman, undated (Box 1)
    - Application for citizenship, undated (Box 1)
    - Klan literature, undated (Box 1)
      "Why?", a flyer opposing Cuban refugee relief funds.
  - Virginia Klan, 1920-1980s (Box 1)
    - "Fusion of the Races or a Mongrel America Tomorrow," delivered by Byron M. Wilkinson, Pastor, Hatcher Memorial Baptist Church, 1960s (Box 1)
    - Klan patronage and recruitment cards, 1920-1968 (Box 1)
    - M. R. Kornegay, Virginia Grand Dragon, rally flyers and informational booklet, 1966 and undated (Box 1)
    - Richmond area recruitment materials and rally poster, 1968 and undated (Box 1)
    - Klan Youth Corps recruiting poster (photocopy), 1980s (Box 1)
    - White Civil-Rights newsletter excerpts, 1980s (Box 1)
    - David Duke profile, distributed by Arlington KKK, 1980s (Box 1)
  - Anti-Klan Material, 1927, 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Shall the Regularly Constituted Authorities or the Ku Klux Klan Rule Alabama?" Address by J.M. Bonner, 1927 Nov. 21 (Box 1)
    - "We Fought the Ku Klux Klan" True Experience Magazine, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous hate literature and ephemera, 1960s and undated (Box 1)
    "Negro's 23rd Psalm," "Scientists Say Negro Still in Ape Stage," "Jews Behind Race Mixing," "Mongrelization--End of Civilization," "The Children of the Devil," "Integration in Schools and Churches," and "Stand Up White People." Also includes a flyer and stickers.
  - Women of the Ku Klux Klan (general), 1920s and undated (Box 3)
    - Klan Haven donation books (blank), undated (Box 3)
      Raising money for an orphanage operated by the Klan.
    - Measurement guide for Klan robes, 1920s (Box 3)
    - Order form for Klan supplies, undated (Box 3)
    - Ladies of the Invisible Empire illustration, Portland, Oregon, undated (Box 3)
    - Membership application forms, undated (Box 3)
    - Women of the KKK passport (blank), undated (Box 3)
  - Women of the Ku Klux Klan Pennsylvania Realm, 1926-1928 (Box 3)
    Official bulletins and correspondence.
  - Women of the Ku Klux Klan Imperial Headquarters, Arkansas, 1926-1928 (Box 3)
  - Women of the Ku Klux Klan certificates and charters, 1934 and undated (Oversize-folder 3)
    - Charter for Kingston, Pennsylvania chapter, 1934 (Oversize-folder 3)
      Includes founding members' names.
    - Klan Regent certificate (blank), undated (Oversize-folder 3)
    - Incorporation certificate for a Junior Preparatory Dept. (blank), undated (Oversize-folder 3)
    - Office holder certificates (2, blank), undated (Oversize-folder 3)
- Serials, 1960s and undated
  - The Fiery Cross, miscellaneous issues, 1960s (Box 1)
  - Viking Age, undated (Box 1)
  - McComb (Miss.) Enterprise-Journal briefs, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - The Klansman, miscellaneous issues, 1980s (Box 1)
  - Klansman (Clansman?) Vol. 2, no. 1, from La Crescenta, California, 1967 (Oversize-folder 2)
- Photographs, 1920s
  Panoramic photographs of Klan meetings and reunions. Includes two copies (one framed, one unframed) of a photograph taken in Gettysburg, 1925.
  - Panoramic photograph of KKK Celebration, Washington, D.C., 8 August 1925 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Acquired through Charles D. Johnson addition.
  - Panoramic photograph of Pennsylvania Klan Reunion, Gettysburg Battlefield, 19-20 September 1925 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Framed panoramic photograph of Pennsylvania Klan Reunion, Gettysburg Battlefield, 19-20 September 1925 (Box 2)
  - Panoramic photograph of KKK Celebration, Miami, 5 July 1926 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Panoramic photograph of KKK on the beach, Miami, 4 July 1927 (Oversize-folder 1)
- Audiovisual materials, Circa 1960s; 0.25 Linear Feet One 1/4-inch open reel audio tape and four phonodiscs in one half-case.
  Access Restrictions
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
  - Sons of Mississippi, "Flight NAACP 105" b/w "High Ride", circa 1960s; 7 minutes
    - Original 45 rpm phonodisc (Box 4, Audio-phonodisc RL10138-PD-0001)
  - Dr. Hiram Wesley Evans, "America's Task," b/w 100% Americans, "America, Our Nobleland," KKK 75004., circa 1930
    - Original 78 rpm phonodisc (cracked) (Box 4, Audio-phonodisc RL10138-PD-0002)
  - Christianity and the Ku Klux Klan, circa 1960s; 83 minutes
    - Original 1/4-inch open reel audiotape (Box 4, Audio-reel RL10138-RR-0001)
  - 100% Americans, "Midnight's Roll Call," b/w "Battle Hymn of the Republic," KKK 75005, circa 1930
    - Original 78 rpm phonodisc (cracked) (Box 4, Audio-phonodisc RL10138-PD-0003)
- Realia, 1950s or 1960s; 2 Linear Feet
  Includes 28-inch ceremonial brass cross.
  - Brass cross, 28 inches, 1950s or 1960s (Box 5)